let's now move to the scheduling for interactive
systems
so this is a list of scheduling strategies
these are discussed in the book
we are going to go through three of them
so let's start with round-robin
we begin by defining a quantum so a time interval
during which
the process can run with run
round-robin the idea is that we let each processor run
for a while
and we're just going in a round-robin fashion as
the name suggests
so we take process one and process to then
process three
that this will take them from the queue of
ready processes
we have
and whenever we start executing our process
we let it run
for a certain period of time the quantum
after that we stop the process and we schedule
the following
one it's simple to implement just keep a list
of ready
processes what is challenging here is to identify
the right
length for the quantum
if you take quantums that are too short then
you have high overhead
because you have to do a lot of context switches
frequently
so you're wasting resources many times to
switch between
processes instead of letting the processes
run
on the other hand if you have a quantum that
is too long
then you will probably affect responsiveness
so if you take this example if you have 50
processes okay
and you look at the last one and you are using
this round-robin
scheduling and the quantum is 100 milliseconds
then
you see that for this process to start it
will take five
seconds and this of course it's not really a
responsive
system if it takes five seconds before a process
gets assigned
to the CPU
so it goes from ready to running actually
because you don't
know it
but it might be that this process is actually
the shortest one
and it's I/O bound
so actually running it in the beginning would
not really
change much for the others but it would make
a significant
difference for this specific process
something we can do is to do something a bit
more accurate or
let's say to have different priorities as
the name suggests
priority scheduling for the different processes
this is based on the assumption which is true
in many
cases that not all processes are equally important
so we assign priorities to the processes
this we can do it statically before they are
started or
this can be also done dynamically
so the priorities can change during the execution
and it can be the operating system that does
this or even the
user that specifies the priority
and we can of course combine priority with round-robin
so it would look something like this
instead of a single list of processes we can
keep several
lists and each list has a certain priority level
here we can assume that the highest priority
means it's more
so the higher value for the priority means it
as a higher priority
then you can start by running for example
in a round robin
fashion you can combine these two the ones
that have priority
for and once all of these are done you can
start running
in a round robin fashion the ones that have
priority three
if everything is done here then you can move
the priority
two and so on
so if you think back at the example I made
about the first
come first serve and why it's not really optimal
for giving
a fair amount of resources and making all
processes finish
rather soon especially if they can you can
see that this
could potentially solve the problem because
you could put
the processes that are I/O bound in the list that
has a higher
priority and then the ones that are CPU bound
in the list
that have a lower priority
think about this
you will see that this would solve the previous
problem
the last one is lottery scheduling
it's nothing different from what the name
is actually saying
it's lottery scheduling
so it's an alternative to priority scheduling
that allows
you to control better how you give resources
to the different
processes each process gets assigned a set
of lottery tickets
okay it's not one
it's not a specific number
you just get a certain number of
tickets
and to decide which is the next process that should
run
the operating system will draw a random choose
a random ticket
and who has the ticket is the one that gets
access to the
cpu so you can imagine that if you want the
process to run
50% of the time and older two processes to
run each 25% of
the time then you can distribute a certain
number of tickets
accordingly to these proportions
and then on the average this is what will
happen when you
use the lottery scattering
so it's easier to map portions of resources
to give to a
process because it is basically the portion
of tickets you give to that process